Okay, let's go ahead and put every dang
thing you need to know about unit four
right into your mind grapes and then
crush them into the sweet nectar of
learning comes pouring forth. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, then I stand at the ready to
milk them. Let's get to it. Okay, so
let's start with the big picture that's
going to tie all the dangly threads of
this overly complex unit together. First
of all, the time period is 1800 to 1848.
The former being the election of Thomas
Jefferson and the latter being the
Seneca Falls Convention. Second, the
theme of this giant honking unit is
pretty simple. The United States gets an
identity. Or to put my interrogative
pants on, we might say the theme is who
is the United States becoming? And
spoiler alert, there isn't just one
identity that emerges, but multiple
concurrent and sometimes competing
identities. Regardless, that identity
question is going to be important for
you to hang on to throughout this review
because we're going to run this thing
thematically instead of chronologically.
So, multiple times throughout this
video, I'm going to be starting at 1800
and go right on through to 1848 and then
the next section, I'm going to go right
back to the beginning and start all
over. So, the thing to keep you oriented
is this: Who is the United States
becoming? And the two massive honking
themes that run throughout this unit and
answer this question are expansion and
war. Or if you like, foreign policy and
economic policy. Okay, so if you're
yucking what I'm yacking, then let's get
to the first answer. Okay, so the first
big strand of American identity that
emerged during this period was the
impulse to become a proper world power
and to get some dang respect on the
world stage. This is the foreign policy
or the expansion theme of American
identity. This was important because
most of the world powers, particularly
European powers, thought the United
States was about as worthy of respect as
a feral raccoon. It's like, yeah, I'm
sure the raccoon plays some kind of
crucial role in the wider ecosystem, but
at the end of the day, you eat other
people's trash. So, here's where I tell
you that during this period, the United
States made strides in at least four
areas and tried their best to rise above
their current trash panda status. First,
the US attempted to increase its power
on the world stage by promoting foreign
trade. So, France and Britain were at
war and were flagrantly ignoring US
neutrality in that conflict. So, Thomas
Jefferson challenged that by passing the
Embargo Act, which really only hurt the
American economy. So, that was a big
whiff, but before James Madison took
office, Congress passed the
Non-Intercourse Act in 1809, which
replaced the Embargo Act. Basically,
instead of cutting off all foreign
trade, the Non-Intercourse Act cut off
trade with Great Britain and France
only. And you know, opening
international trade helped the economy
somewhat, but it didn't have any
dramatic effects and is generally
considered a failure to address the
nation's economic woes. And then there
were other foreign policy attempts to
force Britain and France to take US
neutrality seriously, but for the most
part, they all failed pretty miserably.
And speaking of failing miserably, if
that reality applies as much to early
19th century US foreign policy as it
does to your AP US grade, then buckle up
cuz I got something for you. Now, this
video is part of a larger set of review
materials I made called the AP US Higher
Learning Review Guide. It's got metric
buttloads of resources that are going to
help you get an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May, and it's going
to help you do that as fast as possible.
So, if that's something that you're
into, check that link in the
description. Okay, so then the second
way the US attempted to claim power on
the world stage was by claiming
territory on the North American
continent. For example, by means of the
Adams-Onís Treaty in 1819, Spain ceded
Florida to the United States and it also
firmed up the western border in the
Louisiana Territory. Also, the
Anglo-American Convention of 1818 was an
agreement between Great Britain and the
United States for joint occupation of
the Oregon Country. And by 1846, a new
treaty would establish US possession of
the Oregon Territory below the 49th
parallel. And so, although there are
many examples I could give you, domestic
territorial expansion was certainly a
victory for the US in terms of world
power. But perhaps the most significant
victory in terms of becoming a world
power occurred in a pair of
developments, namely a war and a policy.
The war was the War of 1812 and it was
yet another contest between the US and
Great Britain. So, sort of like American
Revolution 2.0. There were many mounting
tensions between the two powers that led
to open conflict, including economic
tensions over policies like the
Non-Intercourse Act and Britain's
refusal to evacuate troops from forts
located on the US frontier. But the real
egg in America's foreign policy sock was
the continuing British practice of
impressment. It meant that when the
British seized American merchant
vessels, they forced Americans to fight
on British Navy ships. And that kind of
insult to American national honor would
not stand. So, the US declared war on
Great Britain and over the course of two
years, both sides secured some victories
and suffered some defeats. But in the
end, the two powers ended the war by
signing the Treaty of Ghent and
basically declared that the war was a
stalemate. Everything went back to the
way it was before the war started. But
one thing emphatically did not go back
to the way it was before the war, and
that, my dear pupils, was America's
place on the world stage. This was now
the second time they had defeated
[music] Great Britain and that got
plenty of Americans positively drunk on
nationalistic feelings. So much so that
the era directly following the war is
sometimes called the Era of Good
Feeling. And so, that led to the fourth
development in which the US aimed to
claim power on the world stage, namely
the issuing of the Monroe Doctrine. So,
James Monroe was elected president in
1816 and with Americans high on the
victory fumes of the War of 1812 and the
significant territorial expansion that I
mentioned earlier, Monroe saw his chance
to puff out the American chest for all
the world to see. So, he announced the
Monroe Doctrine, which declared that the
Western Hemisphere was a US sphere of
influence. And basically, that means
that he was saying that anything that
happens over here is the business of the
United States and European intrusion
would be very much not welcome. And on
the flip side, he declared that the US
wouldn't meddle in European affairs,
either. And so, in terms of American
identity, I think we can safely say that
the United States made its first steps
toward becoming a proper world power
deserving of respect of other major
European powers. Okay, now the second
major strand of the emerging American
identity during this period was the
development of a modern economy.
Because, to quote James Monroe, you
can't take over the Western Hemisphere's
crap unless you got the boom-boom to
back it up. In case it's not clear, he
did not say that. Please do not write
that down. Anyway, the big honking
development that ushered the US into the
modern world economically was the Market
Revolution. Now, by definition, the
Market Revolution describes the process
through which the United States economy
transitioned from a primarily
agricultural subsistence-based economy
to an industrial commercial economy. And
if that made precisely zero sense to
you, then let me try to Heim explain it
in a way that you might understand. So,
an economy driven by subsistence
agriculture means that most people are
farmers and that they themselves grow or
make everything that they need to
survive. But an economy driven by
commercial industry means that goods are
mass-produced, everything from shirts to
wheat, and then sold to consumers on the
market. It's a transition from
self-reliance to market reliance. So
says you, how did that happen? Well says
I, I'm in the mood to tell you.
Essentially, the Market Revolution had
four big causes. The first cause was the
rise of the factory as the center of
industrial production. So, it was a
British immigrant named Samuel Slater
who created the first textile factory in
the United States and it was able to
produce yarn at a pace that far exceeded
yarn spun by hand. But it was Eli
Whitney who truly revolutionized
American manufacturing by introducing
goods made with interchangeable parts.
Basically, he developed the process by
which manufactured goods could be
fabricated one piece at a time and then
assembled, and this had two
implications. First, since each part was
made with precise machining, it could be
exchanged for any other part on that
item. Second, the main work was done by
machines and therefore the human workers
could be entirely unskilled, unlike an
artisan that made goods by hand from
beginning to end. And so, Whitney
created the blueprint for a more
organized and productive creation of
goods known as the American System of
Manufacture. All right, the second cause
of the Market Revolution was the
development of a metric buttload of new
technology. Industrial factory steam
engines eventually powered machines,
which meant that factories could now be
built anywhere, and oh did they multiply
rapidly. And then we got the telegraph
in 1844, which harnessed short
electrical signals to communicate at a
distance. And as more and more miles of
telegraph wire were hung, distant cities
and markets were able to communicate
with each other almost instantly, and
that led to an even greater tightening
of America's increasingly complex
regional business relationships. But new
technology also reached farmers and
increased their productivity as well.
For example, Cyrus McCormick's
mechanical reaper revolutionized Western
agriculture and led to greater
productivity for the farmers who
specialized in food production for the
United States since this machine could
do the harvesting work of five farmers
harvesting by hand. And then the third
cause of the Market Revolution was the
multiplication of government-sponsored
infrastructure, and there are three
varieties that you're going to need to
know. First, government sponsored the
construction of roads. For example,
there was the development of the
Cumberland Road, which was one of the
rare cases in which a road was financed
by the federal government, and I'm going
to say more about that later. But state
governments also got in on the road
construction party, as did Pennsylvania
with the construction of the Lancaster
Turnpike. But then the second kind of
infrastructure that abounded during this
period was canal. The big example here
was the Erie Canal, which linked Albany
to Buffalo in New York. And then third,
we begin to see the multiplication of
railroads. So, by the 1830s, railroads
were competing heavily with canals as
the most efficient means of regional
economic interconnection. And thanks to
steam-powered locomotives, goods and
passengers could be transported quickly
and cheaply across the United States.
Okay, so the main thing to remember
about all of this new infrastructure is
that it connected the various regions of
the United States, and in doing so, it
made goods easier to ship to regional
markets, and thus the national economy
grew rapidly. And finally, the fourth
cause of the Market Revolution was
urbanization and immigration.
Urbanization means that the population
of America's cities were growing
rapidly, and that's precisely because
cities were home to industrial
manufacturing. So, as the economy became
more and more commercial, subsistence
farmers and their families could no
longer make a viable living as they
always had, and so they migrated to
industrial cities in huge numbers
looking for work. But arguably, an even
more significant contribution to the
success of the Market Revolution was the
spike in immigration during the first
half of the 19th century. Between the
1820s and 1840s, more than 2 million
European immigrants arrived to the
United States, the bulk of which were
Irish, German, or Scandinavian. And for
the most part, these immigrants settled
in big cities in the Northeast, though
some migrated westward as well. And in
settling in these urban areas, the
cities became even more socially
diverse. Furthermore, the spike in
immigration was intimately connected to
the Market Revolution since those who
settled in the northern cities,
especially the Irish, provided an influx
of cheap labor for factories, which
powered the Market Revolution. Okay, so
now let's consider the multitudinous
effects of these two big developments.
Now, remember, we're talking about
expansion and economics, and those two
massive elements of historical change
during this period changed a whole lot
of other stuff as well, and I reckon
it's time to have a look at it. Okay, so
as a result of those two big
developments that I just mentioned, the
United States became a modern democracy,
and all that started with the election
of our boy Thomas Jefferson in 1800. And
you know, this was kind of a big deal
since this signified the first peaceful
transfer of power between rival factions
in this fair nation, which was a signal
that the Republican system of government
could in fact work despite political
differences and disagreements. In this
case, the Federalists surrendered power
to the Democratic Republicans. So, the
US is a country that peacefully
transfers political power, but even so,
you didn't think these parties weren't
going to keep fighting over policies
like toddlers smacking each other over
the family's one iPad, did you? Don't be
crazy. No, these rival factions
continued to debate over at least three
perennial issues. First, they fought
over America's proper relationship to
European powers. A good example here is
Jefferson's Embargo Act of 1807, which I
mentioned briefly earlier. But to suss
it out a little more, Britain and France
were at war, which for them is just like
any normal Tuesday in world history. And
so, Jefferson reaffirmed Washington's
neutrality stance for the United States,
but Britain and France were not in fact
respecting US neutrality on account of
the French were seizing US merchant
ships and the British were forcing
American sailors to fight on their
ships. So, Jefferson convinced Congress
to pass the Embargo Act, which cut off
all foreign trade with the United States
in an effort to force the British and
the French to respect US neutrality.
Guys, I'm a BIG BOY NOW. STOP. BUT
here's where I tell you that the Embargo
Act was a giant turd sandwich, and it
actually did the opposite. So, while it
did improve US manufacturing and thus
paved the way for the market revolution,
for the most part, the Embargo Act
wrecked the US economy. And that led a
fiery debate between the rival parties
about how Jefferson had used federal
power not merely to regulate trade, but
to shut down the whole thing entirely,
not to mention agitate international
tensions with important trading
partners. And then second, the parties
debated over the proper limits of
federal power domestically. And here,
the best example is the Louisiana
Purchase in 1803. Now, long story short,
the French emperor Napoleon Bonaparte
lost interest in France's North American
territory and decided to sell this
massive chunk of land to the US. Now,
Jefferson agreed to the purchase, but
then got real sweaty because of two
opposing principles afflicting him. On
one side, Jefferson and his ilk were
strict constructionists, which meant
that they believed that federal power
was strictly limited to the exact words
of the Constitution. As it turns out,
the Constitution did not grant the
president, nor Congress for that matter,
the authority to purchase land from a
foreign government. But on the other
side, Jefferson's vision for the future
of America was an agrarian future, which
is to say, it was all about farming and
agriculture. So, this doubling of the
United States territory meant that the
West could now fill itself with
frolicking Jeffersonian farmers as far
as the eye could see. And that's the
side that eventually won out. And to
further federal control over this new
territory, Jefferson commissioned
Meriwether Lewis and William Clark to
explore and map the northwestern part of
the land, and Zebulon Pike to explore
and map the southwestern part of the
land. And both of these expeditions
greatly increased the knowledge of the
land and the peoples of the West, which
would help all the more with future
westward expansion efforts. And then
third, parties fought over the proper
scope of federal power in the judicial
branch. Now, if you recall, the
Constitution didn't have much to say
about the duties and powers of the
Supreme Court, and that meant that in
the beginning of this period, the court
really wasn't equal in power to the
other two branches. But under the
leadership of Chief Justice John
Marshall, the court was about to unlock
its latent beast mode and claim its
equal place among the federal
government. And how, says you, did this
happen? Well, says I, in a lot of ways,
but I'm only going to mention two.
First, in the 1803 case Marbury v.
Madison, Marshall led the court to claim
its primary power, namely judicial
review. And by definition, that means
that the court can decide whether a law
violates the Constitution or not. And
then the second case that strengthened
federal power under Marshall was
McCulloch v. Maryland in 1819, which in
some declared that federal laws are
supreme over state law. In other words,
when federal and state laws are in
contradiction, federal laws always win.
Or to put it the other way around, this
case established the precedent that
state laws cannot interfere or overrule
federal laws or power. Okay, so to sum
up, the first way the US is becoming a
modern democracy during this period was
by defining the powers of the
government. And then the second movement
during this period that helped US claim
its identity as a modern democracy was
the expansion of voting rights. And
that's not too hard to understand
because after all, Americans just got
done fighting an entire dang revolution
because, you know, liberty. And maybe
the most tangible sign of liberty is the
right to vote, also known by its sassier
name, the franchise. But here's where I
tell you that in the beginning of the
19th century, in most cases, the
franchise was restricted to white
land-owning men. But it was the Panic of
1819 that changed all of that. Now, this
was essentially a nationwide economic
depression that was caused by a series
of irresponsible practices carried out
by the Second Bank of the United States.
Now, this bank, of course, was like the
bank of the United States, and it
wielded a whole lot of federal power.
And so, when its decisions caused a heap
of economic suffering for nearly all
Americans, the vast majority of which
could not vote in order to hold the
shysters in charge accountable, that
presented a problem. And thus began a
nationwide push to remove property
qualifications for voting and enact
universal white male suffrage. And yes,
it's true that women and black Americans
suffered economically as well, and they
also did not have the right to vote. But
to quote Martin Van Buren of New York,
who led the public charge toward
universal white male suffrage, let's not
get crazy, y'all. Anyway, Van Buren
argued that universal white male
suffrage was already present in the
western frontier states, since they had
organized their territories on that very
principle. Anyway, by 1825, the majority
of states on the eastern coast had
either eliminated or significantly
reduced property qualifications for
voting, even though such a move was
opposed by the propertied elite, who had
formally held the sole privilege of the
franchise. Okay, so, who is the United
States becoming? It's becoming a nation
of voters, an expanded democracy.
However, I need to tell you about a
massive effect of this expansion of the
franchise, namely the development and
growth of America's political parties.
So, one major effect of opening the
right to vote to more people is that
politicians and political parties have
to adjust their platforms in order to
appeal to more people who likely have
very different interests than those
swanky landed elites. And that is
exactly what we see during this period.
Now, by about 1815, the Federalist Party
was altogether deadzies on account of
they opposed a very popular war, namely
the War of 1812, of which I'll have more
to say later. So, that left the US with
a single political party, namely the
Democratic-Republicans, but they
themselves were split into two rival
factions that would eventually become
new political parties themselves. Yeah,
the Democrats led by Andrew Jackson and
the National Republicans led by Henry
Clay. Now, the Democrats were
essentially
National Republicans were the
Federalists 2.0. And that's what you're
going to continue to see as new parties
develop and change names and all of
that. At their core, they are just
really riffing on the themes set up by
the OG political parties. And what are
those themes? Well, if you're in the
mood for me to punt all nuance from the
conversation, and I know that you are,
then the oversimplified version is this.
One party is always going to favor more
government power, and in the beginning,
that was the Federalists and now the
National Republicans. And then the other
party is always going to favor less
government power, and in the beginning,
that was the Democratic-Republicans, and
in this period, it's the Democrats.
Okay, now by the election of 1828, the
new parties had fully formed. The
election was a contest between Andrew
Jackson of the Democratic Party and John
Quincy Adams of the National
Republicans. And here's where we see the
real consequences of that flurry of
expanded democracy. Like, think about
it. Now that it's not just wealthy,
land-owning white men that can vote,
there's a metric buttload of common,
less educated white men who want to have
a say in who becomes the president. And
that means that the candidates and their
parties needed to change the way that
they appealed to the electorate. Well,
as it turns out, John Quincy Adams,
though he was the incumbent, didn't see
fit to get his hands dirty and appeal to
the uneducated rabble, although his
supporters had no qualms about hurling
plenty of slander about Jackson. But
Jackson, well, that guy knew exactly how
to appeal to the common man and did so
by directly campaigning to the people.
Adams, on the other hand, was cold and
aloof and sat in his office and was all,
"If you want me, you know where to find
me." And it's probably not going to
surprise you to hear that Jackson and
his popular appeal to the common people
absolutely destroyed Adams, and Jackson
became the president. Now, here's where
things get pretty interesting. While
Jackson fought for and benefited from
America's expanded democratic impulses,
he also wielded federal power like
Thanos with all five Infinity Stones.
And in a lot of ways, I hope this
reminds you of Thomas Jefferson, since
he also acted in ways that seemed to
contradict his desire to limit federal
power. Both presidents seemed to agree
that federal power should be diminished
in some ways, like in the economy, for
example. But both presidents also felt
as though federal power ought to be
expanded when acting in the best
interest of the nation. I'm going to
give you three significant examples of
Jackson getting positively drunk on
executive power, but also one example of
him restraining executive power. First,
Jackson expanded federal power during
the Nullification Crisis. Long story
short, a tariff was in place which put
serious economic strain on the southern
states, and they hated it so much that
they called it the Tariff of
Abomination. Now, eventually, South
Carolina asserted the right to nullify
this tariff, since they believed it to
be unconstitutional on account of it
seemed like the federal government was
trampling all over the liberty of states
and needed to back way off of its
heavy-handed economic policies. And they
puffed out their chest against Jackson
and said that if the federal government
tried to enforce the collection of this
tariff, South Carolina would go ahead
and secede from the Union. But Jackson,
in no mood to get sass by a measly state
government, led Congress to pass the
Force Bill, which gave Jackson authority
to send federal troops into South
Carolina in order to collect those
taxes. But he also told South Carolina
that he'd work to reduce the tariffs,
and so that diffused the situation and
South Carolinians backed down. Okay, now
the second way Jackson expanded
executive power was during the Bank War.
Now, just before the election of 1832,
the charter for the Second Bank of the
United States was up for renewal, and
Jackson aimed to veto the new charter.
He branded the National Bank as a
monster that benefited elites and harmed
ordinary Americans. And he didn't have
to work that hard to convince common
Americans that this was true, because,
you know, the Panic of 1819 was still
fresh in everybody's memory. Therefore,
Jackson vetoed the charter and killed
the federal bank. And in doing so, he
removed federal deposits from the bank
and deposited them in state banks whose
electorate had been loyal to him, and
that's why Jackson's enemies referred to
them as his pet banks. Okay, the third
example of Jackson's expansion of
executive power came in the form of
policies aimed at American Indian
removal from the United States. Now, in
case you don't know, before becoming
president, Jackson gained his war hero
status, at least in part, by being a
fierce Indian fighter, which is to say,
he was no friend of Native Americans.
And that became clear after the passage
of the Indian Removal Act of 1830. Now,
this was a policy that targeted the
removal of many different American
Indian groups from the United States,
but I just want to focus on one
particular example, namely the Cherokees
of Georgia. So, the Cherokee people had
adopted a policy of assimilation to
white American culture under the
leadership of their chief, John Ross. In
other words, they decided that their
best bet for continuing to live in their
ancestral lands was to become culturally
similar to Americans. So, they created a
Republican government and learned to
speak English and dressed in
American-style clothing. it turned out,
all those efforts did not protect them
when gold was discovered on their land,
and Georgians got real hungry to gobble
up their territory. And in the end, the
Cherokee took to the judicial system,
and in a case called Worcester v.
Georgia, the Supreme Court ruled that
Cherokee removal was unconstitutional.
And we should just take a second to
appreciate what a massive and important
win this was for the Cherokee. Like,
what? But they couldn't bask in the
victory for too long, because Jackson
went ahead and ignored John Marshall's
decision and removed the Cherokee
anyway. And the path was more than a
thousand miles long and led them to the
western side of the Mississippi River
and because so many American Indians
died on the brutal trek it became known
thereafter as the Trail of Tears. Now,
that was an example of American Indians
peacefully resisting Jackson's removal
policy, but in other cases things got
violent as it did in the Black Hawk War
in 1832. So, in that case Jackson sent
federal troops into western Illinois to
force the Sauk and Fox nations to move
westward. And so, their chief Black Hawk
retreated into the Wisconsin territory
and then gathered a thousand fighters to
meet US troops at Bad Axe. And in the
end the result was a massacre American
Indians and the forced removal of the
survivors. Okay, the fourth example of
Jackson's use of federal power actually
has him upholding state power and that
occurred when he opposed federally
funded internal improvements. The big
example to remember here is the
Cumberland Road, otherwise known as the
National Road. So, the National
Republicans and later the Whigs approved
of federal spending on this interstate
road because it would facilitate both
westward migration and help connect
western farmers to eastern markets. But,
the Democrats led by Jackson invoked the
fear of growing federal power at the
expense of the states. They believed an
interstate road to be unconstitutional
because the Constitution did not
explicitly grant that power to Congress.
Okay, so let's just sum up this whole
section. During this period the United
States forged an identity as a modern
democracy through the expansion of
voting rights while at the same time
trying to determine the proper balance
between federal and state power. Easy
peasy, lemon squeezy. Okay, now the
Market Revolution was emphatically not
just an economic development. No, it
caused enormous changes in how many
Americans lived as well, which is to say
in terms of identity the United States
was becoming a modern society. And it
just so happens that you need to know
three aspects of that society. So, let's
talk about it. First, the Market
Revolution led to the emergence of three
distinct social classes. On top was the
business elite, which was the smallest
and wealthiest class. These folks tended
to be factory owners or shipping
executives or something like that. Then
in the middle was the, you know, middle
class and you really need to remember
that this class did not exist before
industrialization in the United States.
So, these people were generally lawyers
or teachers or managers or some other
profession like that. And in general
they were not as wealthy as the business
elite, but they were wealthier than the
working class and that extra boom boom
gave them the occasion to carve out a
distinct social identity, especially in
terms of gender and family relations.
For example, middle class men and women
were increasingly understood to have
separate spheres of existence and
responsibility. The male sphere was
defined by work outside the home and the
female sphere was defined by domestic
work inside the home. So, in this way it
was kind of a status symbol to a middle
class man to have a wife who didn't have
to work because that meant that he made
enough money to support everyone and he
was a real man. And to be clear, this
kind of gender separation was not in
fact present in the lower working class
since those families needed income from
both genders to survive, which I guess
makes working class males fake men?
Anyway, the consequence of this separate
spheres kind of thinking in the middle
class led to a related phenomenon in
terms of women. Basically, it answered
the question, if middle class women
don't work, then what are they good for?
And the answer came in the form of the
cult of domesticity, which said that a
woman's role in the family was to raise
virtuous children and to serve her
husband because, you know, he's the one
out there doing the real work. Okay,
that's enough about the middle class.
So, let me introduce you to the working
class. This class was composed of the
bulk of urban Americans who worked in
factories for pitifully low wages, which
is why they were sometimes referred to
as wage slaves. A big portion of this
class was made up of all those
immigrants that I mentioned earlier. For
example, many of the Irish immigrants
settled in the northeastern industrial
cities like Philadelphia and New York
City. They took whatever jobs they could
find, which usually meant very meager
wages in industrial factories. And even
though these immigrants were vital to
the success of the Market Revolution,
their sheer numbers got some native-born
Americans a real twitchy. This is what
we call a nativist backlash and these
nativists targeted the Irish for many
reasons, not the least of which was
their Catholicness. But, also young
women made up a significant portion of
the working class. In fact, by the late
1820s several entire towns devoted to
manufacturing were constructed in New
England, the most famous of which was
located in Lowell, Massachusetts. So,
the sponsors of this town recruited
young farm girls, who became known as
Lowell girls, from the countryside to
work in their factories and to live in
their town. In the beginning quite a few
of these girls enjoyed the adventure of
leaving home and earning a living. But,
over time working conditions degraded
and they organized themselves into a
union known as the Lowell Female Labor
Reform Association, which was the first
women's labor union in the United
States. All right, so the Market
Revolution stratified American society
into a rigid class structure, which is,
you know, it's always fun to talk about.
But, now I need to tell you about the
second ingredient in the development of
a modern American society, namely a
national culture expressed through art
and philosophy. Without getting too far
into the weeds, you just need to
remember that before, during and just
after the American Revolution American
culture was pretty much all borrowed
from European culture. But, not in this
period, my dear pupil. No, after the War
of 1812, which as I mentioned earlier,
America entered an intense period of
nationalism known as the Era of Good
Feeling. point in the video you know
that it was emphatically not puppies and
rainbows for everyone living in America,
but still a lot of people felt real good
and wanted to show forth those warm
fuzzies and unique cultural expressions.
So, first let's talk about the
expression of American culture through
the arts. Now, the movement that really
influenced these new American
expressions was Romanticism, which began
as a European movement. It was a
reaction to the cold, angular,
dispassionate thinking that
characterized the Enlightenment. In
contrast, Romantics emphasized emotional
exuberance and imaginative exploration
and spontaneity. In other words, they
were real feely feely. And you can see
this in American visual art during this
period, especially in the Hudson River
School, whose artists made nature their
subject and painted majestic American
landscapes that called for more of an
emotional response from the viewer. You
can also see this impulse in literature,
like for example, in the novels of James
Fenimore Cooper. His book The Last of
the Mohicans romanticized the
opportunity and danger of the mysterious
western lands of America. His aim was to
contrast what he called the natural men
of the frontier with the men who had
been corrupted by civilization. And then
in terms of architecture in this period,
American architects designed buildings
in the Greek Revival style. It was
inspired by the Greek Revolution against
the Ottoman Empire during this same time
period and was an homage to the two
countries' mutual love of democracy.
Okay, now the second major cultural
movement during this period was the
development of a unique American
philosophy known as Transcendentalism.
It was conceived of and led by folks
like Henry David Thoreau and Ralph Waldo
Emerson and this way of thinking was
also deeply influenced by the emotional
emphasis of Romanticism. It was a clear
rejection of the rationalism of
Enlightenment thought, which said that
truth can be known through the senses,
like through observation and
experimentation. Transcendentalists, on
the other hand, believed that truth was
beyond the senses or transcended them
and therefore must be accessed by other
means, chiefly by communion with the
mysteries of nature. And then finally,
the third major ingredient to the
emerging American identity during this
period was the impulse to social reform.
Now, there are a whole lot of reforms
that I'll tell you about, but first you
need to know about the religious revival
that created the conditions for reform
and that was the Second Great Awakening.
Now, I could yap for days about the
similarities and differences between
this and the First Great Awakening that
we talked about in Unit 2. But, to keep
things simple, just remember this. The
emphasis of the First Great Awakening
was to reform your nasty, sinful self.
But, the emphasis of the Second Great
Awakening was to reform the entire
nasty, sinful society. Now, mass
religious movements like this are not
without their causes and you need to
know three of them. First, the Awakening
was facilitated by the spread of
democratic beliefs. Now, remember what I
said earlier, namely that there was a
big push to expand democracy during this
period so that even common people could
participate politically in the United
States. Well, that commitment showed up
in the Second Great Awakening as well.
For example, revivalist preachers
organized camp meetings where people
could come and hear preaching and
singing all day long. Some of these
preachers were lower class and some were
uneducated and the camp meeting crowds
themselves were a mixture of races and
classes and wealth. Okay, a second cause
of the Awakening was Americans' embrace
of Romanticism and all the emotional
exuberance thereunto appertaining. For
example, arguably the Second Great
Awakening's greatest preacher was
Charles Grandison Finney, who focused
his efforts in northern cities. He made
use of highly charged emotional language
and spoke in plain language filled with
metaphors and allusions that common
people could understand. Now, the
overarching theme of Finney's preaching
was the possibility of Christians
ushering in the perfect kingdom of God
on earth by means of Christians' moral
efforts to reform society of evils like
alcohol and slavery. And this revival,
much like its first iteration during the
colonial period, swept the country in a
mass movement of common religion. But,
in some cases the religious fervor led
to the creation of new forms of faith
that were at times at odds with the
majority Christian views. And probably
the best example here is the creation of
the Church of Latter-day Saints, whose
people are known as the Mormons. Now,
their founder Joseph Smith had a deep
religious experience under these
revivalist preachers and then began
having visions of his own. As a result,
he created a new church and the people
of New York got real twitchy about some
of their doctrines, most notably their
emphasis on polygamy or, you know, like
multiple wives. Now, ultimately the
Mormons would exile themselves all the
way out in the Utah Territory, where
under the leadership of Brigham Young
they established a proper theocracy. So,
all this to say, people got real
religious during this period and because
this movement emphasized social
reformation, people got busy reforming
the crap out of American society. So,
you know, now it's time to talk about
that. Okay, so the first effect of the
Second Great Awakening was the formation
of utopian societies. For example, the
Oneida Community was created in 1848 in
New York. founder was John Humphrey
Noyes, who had himself experienced a
profound Christian conversion under the
preaching of Charles Finney and was
taken by the impulse to social reform
that came along with it. And what he did
with that impulse was to create a
community of Christians separate from
the wider society in which the
perfection of the kingdom of God could
be practiced. And for them that meant
that all members surrendered their
property to the group and were
encouraged to participate in complex
marriage, which is to say they had
relations with any dang person they
wanted. But, like many of the other
utopian experiments of this age, the
community fell on hard times financially
and were forced to disperse. Okay, the
second effect of the Awakening was the
formation of new voluntary
organizations, which worked to reform
various aspects of society. And one of
the biggest reform movements was the
Temperance Movement, which sought to
curb or eliminate entirely the
production and consumption of alcohol in
the United States. And to that end,
middle class clergy and businessmen
founded the American Temperance Society
in 1826, which aimed to reform
drunkenness among working class men. And
don't miss that nuance there. Temperance
was largely a middle class movement
aimed at the working class. And if you
remember, a not insignificant portion of
that working class were Irish and German
immigrants, who were none too happy
about those well-to-do dinguses trying
to control what the immigrants
understood as part of their culture.
Nevertheless, temperance movements made
a pretty significant impact in many
places with several states enacting
prohibition laws. And then third, this
impulse towards social reform led to the
beginning of a women's rights movement.
Now, women played a significant role in
the abolitionist movement, but on the
whole it was largely a male-led
enterprise. Even when women pushed for
leadership roles in abolitionist
organizations like the American
Anti-Slavery Society, the men in charge
rejected their inclusion. So some
influential abolitionist women began to
discern that their passion and talents
for abolition could only be fully
realized if they had equal rights with
men. Therefore, in 1848, Lucretia Mott
and Elizabeth Cady Stanton organized the
Seneca Falls Convention to address this
very issue. The women at the meeting
produced and signed the Declaration of
Sentiments, which argued for women's
full equality with men in all areas of
society, including employment,
education, and most of all, the
franchise. However, although this first
iteration of the women's rights movement
was born out of the abolitionist
movement, the call for women's rights
was still over time focused on white
women. Regardless, if we're asking the
question, "Who is the United States
during this period?" then we can add
this to the various strands of identity.
Americans were a nation of social
reformers. Okay, now the next way
Americans were reckoning with their
identity played out in the tension
between national interest and regional
interest. In other words, as I am want
to say, the big question Americans were
trying to answer was, "Are we the United
States or the United States?" Okay, so
first let's consider the factors that
contributed to the unification of the
country, and here let's talk economics.
First was the development of a more
national economy. And the big movement
under this heading was the introduction
in 1824 of Henry Clay's American System.
It was a series of policy proposals that
sought to grow the US economy and
further knit together the regional
economies into a tighter interdependent
national economy, particularly after the
War of 1812, when Americans were all
giddy during the Era of Good Feelings.
And so the American System aimed to
boost the national economy by means of
three major initiatives. First was
federally funded infrastructure
projects, including roads and canals
that would specially benefit farmers on
the frontier. Second, the American
System called for protective tariffs.
And here the granddaddy of them all was
the Tariff of 1816. And yes, I know I
said that the American System was
introduced in 1824, but Clay made the
continuation of this tariff a big part
of his plan. Anyway, all you really need
to know about this tariff is that it was
the first tax on imports whose main goal
was not to raise revenue for the federal
government, but instead to protect and
bolster domestic industry. And then the
third part of the American System was
the Second Bank of the United States.
purpose of the federal bank was to
regulate public credit issued through
local banks throughout the nation.
Additionally, the bank issued a national
currency, all of which aimed to bind the
various regions of the country together
into a tighter economic whole. And yes,
this was the very same bank that Andrew
Jackson dubbed a monster and vetoed into
oblivion. Okay, so as a result of these
kinds of policies, there was definitely
an emphasis on America as the United
States. Like, we're becoming a nation
here, y'all. But here's where I tell you
that those efforts aimed at national
unification simultaneously encouraged
regional specialization. What you
talking about, Willis? Well, since the
infrastructure to connect the various
regions was multiplying rapidly, that
meant that each region could specialize
in what they did best and then rely on
importing goods from other regions to
make up for what they lacked. For
example, southern states specialized in
agriculture, and in this period cotton
gradually became the dominant crop grown
and then exported from the South. The
northern states majored in manufacturing
and depended on importing raw materials
from the South in order to produce those
manufactured goods. And then the western
states and territories majored in
growing food, which they exported to the
other regions. So regional economies
were for sure becoming more distinct
from one another, but that also in turn
made them more united because they
needed each other in order to prosper.
But then at the same time, these
differences often caused division when
policies like the American System showed
up, which seemed to benefit some regions
at the expense of others. But without a
doubt, the most divisive issue that made
regional differences flare up was
slavery, to which I say, uh, no duh.
Now, slavery was the dominant labor
system in the South and to a much
smaller degree, the West. But the
dominant labor system in the North was
free wage labor. And hey, you might
think that each region could just look
at each other and say, "Hey, you do you,
boo." But neither region could in fact
do you, boo, because of a very
significant problem. You see, these
regional interests were held in balance
by the equal split of senators in
Congress that represented free and slave
states. So when the Missouri Territory
applied for statehood, it created an odd
number of states, and that led to a
crisis for this delicate regional
balance. To southerners, if northern
states gained an advantage in the
Senate, then the very existence of
slavery would be threatened, and they
had built their entire lives on slavery.
And so ultimately, the debate was
settled by our boy Henry Clay, who
proposed the Missouri Compromise,
otherwise known as the Compromise of
1820. And here's how it solved this
fractious regional debate. Missouri
would be admitted as a slave state, but
Maine was admitted as a free state in
order to preserve the balance in the
Senate. And then it was agreed that
hereafter the 36°30' line of latitude,
Missouri's southern border, would create
the geographical division of slavery in
the western United States. And so the
compromise worked to stop the bleeding
from the gushing neck wound that was the
fight over American slavery. But don't
worry, that bandage is going to pop
right off in the next unit. So if we're
asking about the identity of the United
States, then we can now say that
Americans were becoming a unified whole
while at the same time becoming more
regionally divided on account of
slavery. Or if you're sassy, and I know
you are, the identity of the United
States is both singular and plural. In
order to get the full picture of this
explosive societal and political
division, you're going to need to
understand the development of regional
attitudes about slavery during this
period. And the big idea here is that
during this period, northern states
moved in the direction of abolition of
slavery, while southern states became
more entrenched in slavery. So let's
start in the South. Now, since the
colonial period, the South organized
itself economically, politically, and
socially around the institution of
slavery, but only a tiny fraction of
southern farmers actually owned enslaved
people. the vast majority of farmers in
the South were known as yeoman farmers,
who worked their own land and could not
afford even a single enslaved person.
And then you had a large population of
poor whites who had no land and just had
to find whatever work they could. So do
not miss the big point here. Like, only
a tiny percentage of southern planters
actually owned enslaved people, but at
the same time, every white person in the
South just naturally put an equal sign
between slavery and the southern way of
life. So how did that happen? Well, as
abolitionist movements began to multiply
in the North and crises like the
Missouri Question arose, elite planters
needed to find a way to unite all
southern whites to resist the
curtailment of slavery, which actually
only benefited a few of them. It was a
tall order, but those wily planters went
ahead and did it by introducing an
ideology of white supremacy. It was a
belief that members of the white race,
regardless of wealth, status, or
education, were fundamentally superior
to members of the black race. And as
this idea began to take root, it united
white southerners, regardless of wealth,
because they all had in common their
pasty whiteness. And then second,
southerners changed understanding of the
morality of slavery. You see, prior to
this period, the general opinion about
slavery, even among elite planters, was
that slavery was a necessary evil. But
in this period, that notion was flipped
180° as politicians like John C. Calhoun
began to argue that slavery was in fact
a positive good, both for the economic
flourishing of the South and enslaved
people themselves. And all this taken
together meant that the South had fully
developed a distinct regional identity
centered on white supremacy and the
perpetuation of slavery. And in tying
slavery to their very identity,
southerners abandoned almost all
possibility for compromise over the
issue. So I'm sure it'll work out just
fine on opposite day. Anyway, up in the
North, it was a completely different
story as they began moving further and
further away from slavery through the
growth of various abolitionist
movements. Now, the earliest advocates
for abolition were, not surprisingly,
black Americans themselves. Free blacks
in the North used various methods to
attack the system of slavery, including
lecture tours, publishing pamphlets, and
assisting in the resettlement of runaway
enslaved people. And one of the fieriest
black pamphleteers during this period
was David Walker. His most popular essay
was called An Appeal to the Colored
Citizens of the World, and in it he
pushed for immediate abolition of
slavery. And if it was not done, then
enslaved blacks would emancipate
themselves by force. But over time, many
white abolitionists joined the cause as
well, and perhaps the sauciest of them
all was William Lloyd Garrison of
Boston, who published his own
anti-slavery newspaper known as The
Liberator. And Garrison drew inspiration
from black abolitionists like David
Walker by arguing for immediate
abolition without a cent of restitution
to enslave. However, Garrison didn't
really jive with Walker's encouragement
and instead emphasized that abolition
must occur by means of persuasion of
people's thinky-thinky part. Anyway, the
efforts of abolitionists had paid off
handsomely by 1820, in which every
northern state had either abolished
slavery entirely or passed gradual
emancipation laws. But the southern
reaction to the spread of the
abolitionist movement was to impose even
greater control over their enslaved
populations. For example, southern
states passed laws making it illegal to
free enslaved people or to teach them to
read and write and prohibited marriage
among the enslaved, etc. And that
shouldn't surprise you, since as I said
earlier, southerners believed that
slavery was the very lifeblood of their
society, and that means that they had to
spread it westward and protect it as
much as possible from those dumb
northern abolitionists. Okay, now you
may have noticed that with all this
mouth-hole flapping I've been doing, I
haven't talked much about a crucial
character in this whole story, namely
black Americans themselves. Well, baby,
now's the time. But first, I need to
mention that both the North and the
South had about an equal population of
free blacks, which is to say, they were
not enslaved. And you might get the
impression that in the anti-slavery
abolitionist North, that white people
were going around hugging all the free
black people, because, you know, slavery
is the worst and all. But not so much.
Free blacks in the North certainly
enjoyed more social equality than those
in the South, but they experienced
racial discrimination and
marginalization all the same. But what
about the huge population of enslaved
black Americans? I mean, were they just
rolling over and accepting their
enslaved lot in life and content to be
powerless pawns on the bitterly divided
American chessboard? Don't be crazy. No,
in fact, you're going to need to know
the various ways in which enslaved
people resisted the dehumanizing effects
of slavery, and that resistance comes in
two flavors. The first is covert
resistance, which is to say, it was more
hidden and subtle. And this includes
everything from breaking tools and
slowing down their work effort to reduce
the planters' profits to secretly
maintaining their own cultural norms,
like calling each other their African
names and worshiping according to their
own manner. But then the second flavor
of rebellion is overt resistance, which
is to say, violent retaliation. And here
I'll introduce you to Nat Turner's
rebellion in 1831. Now, long story
short, Nat Turner, in the eyes of his
owners, was submissive and deferent as
an enslaved man should be. But below
that facade, Turner believed he was a
prophet who had received a mission from
God to incite a slave rebellion. And so
one night, he gathered his followers,
and they launched a reign of terror
throughout the Virginia countryside.
Turner killed the white family who
claimed ownership over him, and then he
and his followers spread throughout the
neighboring farms and ended up killing
more than 50 white men, women, and
children. Now, in the end, the Virginia
militia put a quick and violent stop to
this rebellion, but it agitated a deep
and abiding fear of white planters that
other rebellions could soon break out.
Therefore, states across the South
imposed much harsher slave codes meant
to restrict and control its enslaved
populations. Okay, so once again, let's
return to the identity question here at
the end of this section. The United
States in this period is becoming more
unified economic policy and regional
interdependence. But at the same time,
the United States is becoming more
plural as the North and South become
increasingly antagonistic over the
subject of slavery. And, I'm sorry to
say that that antagonism is just going
to get nastier in the next time period.
So, you know,
something to look forward to. Well,
okay, you can click here to grab my A
push Heimler review guide, or you can
click here to watch my other more
detailed videos on unit four. Congrats
on getting through this one, and I'll
catch you on the flip flop. I'm out.